[MUSIC]
Hi!
Welcome, thanks for
coming to the psychology of popularity.
I'm glad that you selected this course.
And I'm excited to tell you about some
of the work that I've been doing and
lots of researchers have been
doing in the area of popularity.
But when we talk about popularity,
a lot of people will sometimes say
is this really a subject that
people study in psychology?
Isn't this just something that
is important in high school or
in adolescence?
What difference does this
really make in the real world?
So maybe a good way to start is for
us to talk a little bit about
how popularity really does
play an important role.
And it plays an important role actually
throughout the entire lifespan.
So, first of all,
of course when we think about who cares
about popularity we think about children.
And in this graphic what you can see is
that even starting at very young ages,
and this graphic is from over 30
years ago, children spend far more
time of their waking hours surrounded by
their peers than surrounded by adults.
And you can see here that between
the ages of about two all the way until
pre-adolescence, there's this dramatic and
increasing tendency for
kids to interact with their peers.
So of course, if those interactions
are aversive, difficult,
filled with victimization that's going to
have a big effect on the developing child.
What you don't see after
this graphic is that
these trends just increase
dramatically into adolescence.
So once kids get into adolescence,
of course, it's totally uncool
to spend any time with adults.
And we see even more increases in
the amount of time spent with peers.
In fact, what we know is that starting
at the age of three, young children can
already tell you which kids are the most
popular, which kids are the least popular,
and which kids are kind of not
affiliating with their peers at all.
So starting from very, very early
in childhood, popularity becomes
a really important construct, a variable,
that really has impact over time.
Now once we pass through childhood and
we get into adolescence,
there are actually some biological reasons
why popularity starts playing a big role.
So what you can see here,
this is a graphic of the brain.
And what we know now is that
from the time that the pubertal
transition starts,
adolescents brains start to mature, but
the whole brain doesn't mature
at the exact same time.
It actually starts in the back and
then the development of the brain
kind of moves up forward.
So what that means is that the parts of
the brain that are developing the most
are the parts that are below the cortex.
In other words, the parts that
are shared with most mammals.
And those things are kind of instinctual
drives and things that you want for
quick rewards.
And one of those pieces in the limbic
system that's really important
is the desire for social rewards.
And the reason why in adolescence
there's this big push for
our brains telling us to go out and
get social rewards,
is because it's a way of helping us
to develop autonomy from adults.
It's basically telling us,
your parents aren't cool anymore.
You want to be able to go out and
learn how to be self sufficient.
You're not going to be taking care of by
your parents for the rest of your life.
So our brains make us really
interested in hanging out with peers,
being very excited about
what happens with peers.
And as a result, we tend to be
very interested in whatever we
can do to make us want to get
rewards from people our age.
And simultaneously,
we become less interested in adults, so
that's totally natural.
Unfortunately all that develops before the
part of the brain in the front that helps
us to exert control over those impulses
and keep us from doing things impulsive.
That doesn't develop until later, so we
don't really see that happen which is why
in adolescence there's lots
of risk taking behavior.
So that's why we see this huge increase
in a desire to do what peers do and
care what peers think in adolescence.
So that's a big part of what's
happening as we grow up.
And of course, when we think about
adolescence usually the things we remember
the most are not the things that
happened with our parents or
the things that happened with
our courses in high school.
But we're really think
about who was popular,
how much was I embarrassed
in front of other peers?
How much can I make sure that I'm meeting
people to be friends with or to date, and
that becomes really important.
So what about with adults?
Well, I mean, one interesting thing
about adulthood is that for some reason,
adults love talking about their
adolescence in terms of popularity.
And if you look at things that
you see on TV, or songs, or
especially movies out there, there are
tons of movies that kind of bring us back
to those times in adolescence.
And we really are talking about
peer relationships and friendships.
There's a reason why we're
really interested in that and
that's from nostalgic value.
But maybe there's a reason why we
also care about popularity as adults.
That has to do with present day.
If you think about it, there are a lot
of ways that in our adulthood life,
we are still thinking about and
probably really affected by popularity.
And hopefully that's why you're here.
You're here so that way you can get
an idea about how popularity is
affecting how happy you are today,
how successful you are today and
how your relationships are going today.
There are a lot of different
ways that we see this and
probably now much more than we
have seen for decades earlier.
We see all this reflected in social media.
So social media is really pulling us
all back into that adolescent world of
caring about who responded
to our Facebook likes and
posts and
how many Twitter followers we have.
And which pictures we put up, and how
many people have paid attention to that.
It's kind of in a way of playing out this
idea of popularity all over again, but
it's doing it in a way that's explicit and
measurable and
there are numbers next to it.
And people sometimes even
get very hyped up about
how often their posts have
been paid attention to.
Or they seem to try and get more
relationships through social media.
So it's affecting us as adults.
It's certainly affecting these
adolescents growing up today.
But it's also affecting us as adults.
Another way that we really
see popularity playing a role
is our big fixation with celebrities.
And if you think about it,
celebrities are kind of the popular
kids in the adult high school.
For some reason, and all you have to
do is go to the grocery store and
kind of see all the magazines there.
We are remarkably concerned
about what they're doing and
what they look like and what they say and
what their opinions are.
This is even a big marketing strategy to
get celebrity endorsers with the idea that
if a celebrity buys a product or
espouses a world view, we might be
more likely to have similar attitudes.
And the reason why is it's playing up
on these same ideas of popularity that
we will see what those people
do as highly influential.
In fact, a lot of marketing
is really geared towards
leveraging the same types of
popularity dynamics in current day.
And when you think about marketing from
the perspective of political marketing.
We're really seeing that when
it comes to campaigns and
presidential campaigns, there's really
a way in which we're trying to be pulled
towards the same types
of popularity politics.
And that really plays an important role.
And it's something that's
effecting our whole culture.
And that has a lot to do with popularity.
But, even if we go beyond
the perspective of the entire culture,
how is popularity affecting your life?
What are things that you are experiencing
every day that have a lot to
do with popularity, as many of us have
studied it, in childhood and adolescence?
Well If you work in an office with other
people, then you've probably noticed
that there are some ways that the office
has some of the kinds of cliques and
groups and
reputations that there was in high school.
It might be far more sophisticated.
It might be presented in a way
that's a little bit different.
No one is kind of playing
on a playground or
teasing kids that have to sit in
the corner of the room in the workplace.
But there are ways in which some people
tend to have much more influence
in meetings, people really want
to hear what they have to say,
they have a way of really
getting people laughing.
They might stand in the door frame having
conversations with their coworkers a lot.
Where as other people,
they're not invited to lunch,
they really aren't someone that
people want to affiliate with.
Turns out that really
affects work performance.
That affects how much the company,
overall, is successful.
That even affects how long people
will stay in their job, and
a lot of that has to do with popularity.
We also see this of course,
play a role in all of our relationships.
So whether it's our
adulthood friendships and
how much we feel we're getting support
from friends in times of stress.
Or how much we feel in
our friendship groups.
There are some people
who tend to be the boss.
And tell everyone what they're doing and
what the plans are and
whose house you're meeting at.
Versus those that tend to still feel
a little bit like they're on the outskirts
of the social group.
Or they're not the ones in
the neighborhood that are often
invited to all of the events.
That's all about popularity too.
In fact, we even see that play a big
role when it comes to romantic partners.
Who you meet, how dating goes,
how we feel during a date.
Then afterwards, our satisfaction
in our marital relationships or
other kinds of romantic partnerships.
A lot of that stems from the things
we learn about popularity.
Of course, for those of us that
are parents, in our adulthood,
we also find that parenting is something
really tied into popularity, as well.
We know that the way that you
experience popularity as a child
as related to the kind of parent you are.
And we also know that it affects you're
own children's level of popularity and
whether they do well at school or
if they don't do as well with their peers.
We also know that how kids
deal with popularity today,
especially in the world of social media,
is very different than how we all dealt
with these things back when we were kids,
way before social media even got started.
So that's something we're
going to talk about as well.
So overall,
what we're going to talk about for
the rest of this course is specifically
why popularity is so important.
Why is it that this is something that we
all seem to care so much about when we're
young, and it continues to play out in
all these different ways in adulthood?
We're going to talk also about how
we study popularity scientifically.
And using that scientific research,
what do we know about what predicts who's
popular across lots of different
settings and across the lifespan?
And how popularity predicts
our life outcomes overall.
And we're going to talk about all of these
things over the course of the next few
lectures so thanks again for joining.
Really excited that you're here and
excited to keep on going
with the next clip.