Jack: Now,
one of the objections
that we get is,
"Nobody can understand it.
Nobody can understand
the King James Bible.
The words are too difficult."
David: That's so funny!
Because people
take college classes
all the time, and
they learn
new vocabulary words.
You pay a lot of money
to a college
for a company
to employ you, and
they teach you
new vocabulary words.
There's only what,
600 words or so
in this?
And that's nothing.
The vocabulary of
the whole King James Bible,
as I've said
in one of my vlogs,
is the amount of vocabulary
of a five and a half year old.
My kids were reading
the King James Bible
at that age.
My friends' kids
actually learned to read
off the King James Bible.
One of my kids also did.
It's not a matter of
difficulty of words.
It's just a matter of
learning them,
just like anything else.
Jack: Well now,
I have another question.
What about
the modern versions,
like the NIV, or
the New King James?
Those are pretty popular.
The ESV is another
popular version now.
Are there any
difficult words in those?
David: There are.
There's a book called
"Archaic Words and
the Authorized Version"
(by Laurence M. Vance). You can
still get a copy of it,
I'm sure.
And it will show you
that all the Bibles
have these kind of words
in them - pretty much
--and you have to learn them
in any Bible.
It's really a fake argument
to get you to say,
"Oh, it's too hard!"
Again,
my kids would say,
"No, it's not."
And it's really sad
when a little kid
can put a scholar
with a Ph.D to shame,
by understanding the Bible
better than he does.
Jack: Interesting.
And you know
it's true,
even when you play sports,
you have to learn a position.
Don't you have to learn
the names of a position?
Or if you're a carpenter,
don't you have to know
what a soffit,
a fascia, or ridge,
any of these things is?
So it's not surprising that
if you're gonna
learn something as important
as the Bible,
that you're also gonna
have to learn
some vocabulary words.
We learn
vocabulary words
in business.
No matter
what business you're in
you get trained and
you learn the nomenclature
of that particular business.
So what a surprise that
you have to learn it
for a Bible
that's more important
than any of
the other things that we do.
So there's one of the things
you can use,
this little Companion dictionary
that can go right in your Bible
if you ever have any questions.
And you'll
pick up the words really quickly,
anyway.