Jack: What about
the Geneva Bible?
That was certainly
a precursor,
because there were
a number of precursor
English Bibles
before the King James,
starting with William Tyndale's
1525 edition New Testament,
and from there,
there was the Matthews Bible (1537),
and Coverdale (1535),
and the Great Bible (1539-41),
and the Geneva (1560),
and the Bishops (1568).
There was also
another one, the Taverner's (1539).
So there were
a number of English Bibles.
And now the question
has come up,
"Well, what about
all those previous English Bibles?"
And especially,
people are talking about
the Geneva Bible.
What does your research
show you about the Geneva?
David: Well, the bottom line:
I call it,
"Close, but no banana."
It's really close.
It has a lot of
really good points to it.
It's based on pretty much
the right text.
But there are
some compromises in it.
And there are
some changes in it.
Sam Gipp has written something
on that ("The 2006 Geneva Bible:
The Trojan Horse") and put
some things together.
I found some stuff
as well with my 1599.
You could look them up.
But the bottom line is
they weren't as literal,
clear with the Hebrew
and the Greek,
so the meaning
could stand up like the KJV.
So you wouldn't
even have to hold
the Hebrew or the Greek.
You have the King James Bible,
now, here,
and you can look through it
and see the language
right there,
because it's
the same meaning.
God transferred it.
But sometimes
they played little games.
They weren't as clear.
They weren't as defined
in giving us
exactly what God said
and kind of paraphrased
a little bit.
And sometimes
they added in
some side doctrines
that actually
are not correct.
The Geneva did it
a few times.
I don't want to get into
all that right now.
Jack: I don't
think that's necessary.
But one of the arguments
for the KJV, or
one of the things
they wanted to accomplish
with the King James Bible,
was that it
wouldn't have any notes.
It wasn't a study Bible,
so to speak.
You should study it,
but it wasn't a study Bible.
David: Well, yeah,
because all the notes
that were in the Geneva,
they really got into
a lot of issues,
kind of like getting
Hal Lindsey's books on prophecy
and somebody else's stuff on politics
and kind of
blending them all together,
and putting them
all in the side notes.
It kind of detracts from
the fact that you want
what God said.
And so when
the King James Bible
was put together,
the idea was that
you read IT.
And, of course,
cross-references help us
as we learn
to read our Bible and
what relates to what.
It was just too many notes
in the Geneva.
And really,
read them for yourself.
Go download it.
Check it out for yourself.
You'll see why
some of them are
just downright silly.
And some of them
--I mean
the world would have ended
a long time before now
if you believed their view
of prophecy. (See Revelation notes, etc.)
Jack: Interesting.
That's good to know.